原视频名：Virgin Reaches Orbit With The Help of Cosmic Girl
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/Yi-fBKK7nME
原视频发布日期：20210119
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
双关梗已经斜体标出，中文不便翻译
And massive congratulations are in order to Virgin Orbit
大力祝贺维珍轨道
who in a matter of speaking lost their orbital virginity on Sunday
说起来 他们在周日首次入轨发射
when they successfully deployed their LauncherOne rocket.
也就是发射器一号火箭的成功发射
It lit its engine and it successfully placed the payloads into orbit
它点燃了发动机 成功地将有效载荷送入轨道
making them the newest addition to a growing list of privately developed launch vehicles.
使之成为了正不断增长的私人开发的运载火箭名单中的最新成员
This was only their second launch attempt
这只是他们的第二次发射尝试
and it was actually carrying a live payload about 10 cubesats for NASA's ELaNa program,
它实际上携带了一个真实的有效载荷 也就是NASA的ELaNa计划中的10个立方星
the Educational Launch of Nano Satellites.
ELaNa全称纳卫星的教育发射
And that demonstrated that they had a lot of confidence
这表明他们有很大的信心
that they had solved the problems in their launch vehicle.
也就是已经解决了运载火箭的问题
youtu.be/PIXsMv1jkzY
The first attempt to launch last year.
在去年的首次尝试发射中
The vehicle dropped from the aircraft
火箭从飞机上掉落
lit its engines and then after a couple of seconds the engine cut out
点燃了它的发动机 然后过了几秒钟 发动机就熄火了
and this was traced to a breakage in the high pressure oxygen line
而这是由于高压液氧管道的断裂造成的
which all resulted in the engine getting starved and of course the flight termination system was activated
这一切的结果是发动机被憋死了 当然飞行终止系统也被激活了
resulting in a fireball that descended into the pacific
火箭变成了火球并坠入太平洋
but all that is a distant memory now.
但这一切 现已成为遥远的记忆
Virgin Orbit have joined a very short list of companies have developed their own private rockets.
维珍轨道已经加入了一个很短的名单 那就是开发了自己的火箭的(美国)私人公司名单
SpaceX Rocket Lab and Orbital ATK which is now part of Northrop Grumman.
这份名单上的其他公司为SpaceX 火箭实验室和现在是诺斯罗普格鲁曼的一部分的轨道ATK
But while they were confident enough to put a customer's payload on it
但是 虽然他们有足够的信心把客户的有效载荷放在上面
they weren't comfortable enough to actually share a live stream publicly.
但还没有足够自信到公开分享直播
We did get the whole thing live tweeted and we got all the details.
我们确实看到了推特直播 并且得到了所有的细节
There was some concern at one point as to whether the satellites had actually separated from the stage
曾经有人担心卫星是否真的从二级上分离了
but eventually we got notification all the satellites were in the correct orbit and flying free.
但最终我们收到了通知 所有的卫星都在正确的轨道上 并自由飞行
but as with many of these things there were actually internal streams and a lot of stuff leaked from these
但与许多这些东西一样 实际上有内部的视频流泄漏出来
and you can actually see the entire launch sequence online.
而且你可以在网上看到整个发射时序
It's very well produced.
它的制作非常精良
But I want to focus on their official footage first.
但我想先关注一下他们的官方视频
Virgin Orbit started out as a spin-off from Virgin Galactic.
维珍轨道是从维珍银河中分拆出来的
They wanted to launch rockets using the White Knight carrier aircraft.
他们想用白色骑士号运载机发射火箭
But their rocket got bigger and instead they asked their investor founder Richard Branson.
但他们的火箭变大了 于是他们问他们的投资人和创始人理查德·布兰森
Hey you run an airline could we borrow one of your old 747s.
嘿 你是开航空公司的 我们能不能借你的一架老的747飞机
And so they got this magnificent creature called Cosmic Girl.
于是他们得到了这架名为宇宙女孩 的壮丽生物
This plane first flew in september of 2001.
这架飞机在2001年9月首飞
It flew on transatlantic routes.
它曾执飞过大西洋航线
I think I actually flew on it at one point.
我想我曾经坐过这架飞机
But it carries the 30 ton rocket underneath the left wing.
但它的左机翼下带着30吨的火箭
The reason is that there's actually a hard point there
原因是那里其实有一个挂载点
where they can carry a spare engine if they need to move the engines between the airports.
如果他们需要在机场之间移动发动机 就可以在那里挂载备用发动机
And so on there there's a quick release system
那么在那里有一个快速释放系统
which includes all the umbilicals to keep the rocket ready for flight.
其中包括所有保持火箭的飞行准备的脐带
It's a liquid propellant rocket so I imagine they must top up the propellant.
这是一枚液体推进剂火箭 所以我想他们必须加满推进剂
When they get to the launch site, they pull up into a steep climb and drop the rocket
当他们到达发射位置时 他们会拉起 进入陡峭的爬升阶段 然后把火箭扔下去
and the plane immediately banks over to the right to clear the area.
而飞机立即向右转弯以让出区域
As the rocket drops, it initially fires a small set of thrusters called propellant settling thrusters
当火箭下落时 它最初会点燃一组小推进器 被称为推进剂沉底发动机
that make sure the engine can light cleanly.
以确保发动机能够干净利落地点火
And then the main Newton 3 engines light up and they generate about 35 tons of thrust.
然后牛顿3主发动机点火 产生35吨的推力
Now this all happens miles off the coast to the west of Los Angeles.
这一切都发生在洛杉矶以西数英里外的海岸线上
And for the first launch it was too cloudy but on Sunday it was wonderfully clear.
第一次发射时云量太多 但周日的时候天气非常晴朗
And there's this magnificent cell phone video showing the actual launch
这段壮丽的手机视频展示了实际的发射过程
and here you can see the trails of the two vehicles
在这段视频中 你可以看到两个载具的尾迹
and if you look you can see the inverted u-shape.
你可以看到那个倒U形的尾迹
That's the trajectory that the 747 followed
那就是波音747的飞行轨迹
but you can now see the rocket heading off to the left.
但你现在可以看到火箭向左边飞去
Now initially and by the time it's lit its engine the rocket is basically going horizontally
在最初发动机点火的时候 火箭基本上是水平前进的
so it needs to pick up vertical speed and it does this by assuming a high angle of attack
因此 它需要提高垂直速度 并通过提高攻角来实现这一点
so it's pointing upwards but the engine thrust isn't what's giving it the vertical speed.
所以它开始向上抬头 但发动机的推力并没有(或者说不完全)给它带来垂直速度
Most of the initial lift comes from the aerodynamic forces
大部分的初始升力来自空气动力学中的作用力
as it slides sideways through the atmosphere at high angle of attack like a wing.
当它在大气层中以高攻角侧滑时 就像一个机翼
It doesn't have a wing.
(尽管)它没有机翼
Pegasus was another air launched vehicle and it had a wing.
飞马座是另一种空中发射的火箭 (但)有机翼
This is entirely a regular shaped rocket with fins.
而发射器一号完全只是一个常规形状的 有尾翼的火箭
So now that let's watch this again.
那么现在我们再看一下这个视频
Watch for the initial propellant settling thrusters and then the main engine.
请看最初的推进剂沉底发动机 然后是主发动机
And then watch the engine gimballing to actually give it the high angle of attack.
然后看发动机的摆动 实际上是让它调整到高攻角的姿态
So propellant settling main engine and then the engine gimbals and the thing takes an angle.
那么先是推进剂沉底发动机(点火) 然后是主发动机(点火) 之后发动机摆动 然后火箭抬头
And so for the first section of flight this rocket is essentially doing an epic power slide through the atmosphere
那么在第一段飞行中 基本上这枚火箭是在大气层中进行史诗般的动力滑行
just trying to eke out a little bit of lift.
只是想凑出一点升力
So it can start heading upwards into the stratosphere and onwards into space.
这样它就可以开始向上进入平流层 然后继续进入太空
From the onboard camera you can see that rocket exhaust pointed upwards to get the torque.
从箭载相机上可以看到 火箭的尾气指向上方 以获得力矩
Once they get enough vertical speed they can just fire the engine straight
一旦获得足够的垂直速度 就不用摆动发动机了
and of course then you have MECO, stage separation
当然还有主发动机关机和一二级分离
and the ignition of the second stage Newton 4 engine which will power the vehicle into orbit.
以及二级牛顿4发动机的点火 而这将驱动火箭入轨
Now for this demo mission, the payload was quite light and the orbit was quite high.
那么对于这次验证任务 有效载荷很轻 而轨道也很高
So they put it into an eccentric orbit
所以他们把它送入了非圆(椭圆)轨道
and then had an engine re-light to circularize it into a 500 kilometer 60 degree orbit.
然后让发动机再次点火 使其进入高500公里 倾角60度的轨道
So it was a success all round.
因此 这是一次完全的成功
And of course the reusable zero stage better known as Cosmic Girl head back to Mojave for future flights.
当然 可重复使用的零级(火箭)宇宙女孩返回了莫哈维 为未来的飞行做准备
I do want to take a moment to look at a few things from the a leak stream
我当然想花点时间看一下 泄漏出的视频流中的一些东西
which was pretty well put together by the looks of things.
里面有很多好康的
Obviously we get the launch and you see the whole ignition sequence
很明显 我们看到了发射 而且你看到了整个点火序列
and the assumption of the high angle of attack mode.
以及高攻角模式的进入
But soon after this engine lights you start to get this roll oscillation
但在这个发动机点火后不久 就开始出现这种滚转波动的现象
and I'm going to say if I was one of the people working on the rocket I would have been terrified by this.
我想说的是 如果我是火箭的研发人员之一 我一定会被这个吓坏的
I would have thought that we are about to lose the vehicle
我会觉得火箭即将解体
but the control systems kept the thing under control
但控制系统让这件事得到控制
and I think just really what this is is it was the first time they had entered this flight region in testing
而我觉得这真的是他们第一次进入这个飞行阶段来进行测试
and when you're performing a high angle of attack maneuver at transonic speeds
而当你在跨音速下进行高攻角机动时
it's very difficult to model.
这是很难建模的
And I'm not surprised that this was one of the reasons they might have run into trouble.
而我觉得这可能就是他们会遇到麻烦的原因之一
And they successfully negotiated and now they have the data they know for future reference.
然而他们成功地搞定了这件事 现在他们有了可供以后参考的数据
I don't see this being a future problem.
(而)我就不认为这个问题还会在以后遇到
The other fascinating thing is this display they popped up on the left
另一件令人着迷的事情是在左边弹出的这个画面
which tells us all sorts of cool things that we speculated on.
它告诉我们之前猜测过的各种很酷的事情
If you look on the left towards the mid to lower region there's a section that says gimbal and turbine roll control.
如果你注意看左边的中下部分 那里写着矢量摆动和涡轮(尾气)滚转控制
This is how they're controlling the launch vehicle during the initial atmospheric ascent.
这就是他们在最初的大气层上升过程中 控制运载火箭的方法
You see like a blue polygon with a purple spot inside it that's showing the gimbal position
你看那个蓝色的多边形 里面有一个紫色的点 就是矢量摆动的位置
and you'll notice it has a big chunk out at the bottom. It points further down
然后你会发现多边形的底部块更大 这样可以向下摆动得更深
because I think they need more authority to be able to pitch up than they do in any other axis
因为我认为俯仰轴需要更多的力度才能把火箭拉起
so they have extra room in their gimballing.
所以下方的摆动空间更大
Underneath that they have an indicator for turbine roll control.
在那下面 还有一个涡轮滚转控制的指示器
I think the turbo pump exhausts are used as little thrusters to provide roll capability.
我认为涡轮泵的尾气是作为小推进器来提供滚转能力的
So we've seen pictures like this showing the rocket nozzle and the two turbine exhausts underneath
那么我们已经看到这样的图片 显示了火箭喷管和下面的两个涡轮尾气管
and there was speculation that this was how they got roll control
而有人猜测 这就是他们获得滚转控制的方法
but it hadn't really been confirmed to many people satisfaction
但这样的说法并没有说服很多人
but I think this is pretty conclusive at this point
但这里我认为这是很有说服力的
that these are definitely being used to provide some sort of thrust vectoring.
这些肯定是用来提供某种推力矢量的
Of course we get much better views of this on the ground on test stands.
当然 在地面上的试车台上可以看到更好的画面
This is a short test to show the controls and the turbine exhausts are the ones coming underneath
这是一个展示控制能力的简短测试 而涡轮尾气从下方排出
and you see that has a much smokier and darker flame
你看 那个烟雾更多 火焰更黑的
because these are exhaust gases that have to drive turbines
因为这些废气得能驱动涡轮
and so they're fuel rich and they're cooler.
所以燃气是富燃的 这样温度更低
But you can also see the main engine running through all its gimbaling
但你也可以看到主发动机在运行过程中的所有矢量摆动
to demonstrate that it was able to control a rocket in these extreme conditions.
以验证它能够在这种极端条件下控制火箭
If you do watch it, realize that there is a significant lag between the telemetry and the video on the right.
如果你之前真的看了这段视频 要知道遥测数据和右边的视频之间有明显的滞后
I've gone and fixed it here using the magic of compositing
我在这里用神奇的剪辑技术修复了它
so we get to see the whole thing coming apart and the display actually matching that in sequence.
所以 我们可以看到一二级的分离时间和视频画面是匹配的
One other thing that I sort of noticed and that is the gimbal for the second stage isn't centered
还有一件事我注意到了 二级的矢量摆动并不是放在中间的位置
so I'm wondering if the payload was asymmetric or something
那么我猜 也许有效载荷是不对称的 或者有别的什么缘故
and they needed to have this thing firing off axis to keep it stable.
而他们需要让发动机离轴点火以保持稳定
So after the successful test, hopefully they will be able to start selling this on to customers.
那么在成功测试后 希望他们能够开始向客户销售这个东西
I believe they already have like three launches for the military signed up under their Vox subsidiary
我相信他们已经有三个军方的发射项目 通过Vox子公司来签署的合同
but I think LauncherOne offers a few advantages over other alternatives
但我认为相比其他竞品 在一些方面 发射器一号更具优势
depending upon your mission requirements.
(当然)取决于你的任务要求
They have slightly more mass and capability than Rocket Lab
发射器一号的质量和运载能力都比火箭实验室(的电子火箭)略高
and while Rocket Lab have made a lot of gains by using their photon third stage
而当火箭实验室通过使用他们的光子三级 取得了很大的收获的同时
Virgin Orbit are also planning on offering a third stage for interplanetary missions
维珍轨道也在计划为行星间任务提供三级(的配置)
and being able to operate from an airport gives them more flexibility.
并且能够从机场进行运作 这给他们带来了更大的灵活性
It is planned that they will be able to launch satellites from the UK at some point in the future.
根据计划 在未来 他们将能够从英国发射卫星
There's a planned facility in Cornwall which will support this.
在康沃尔有一个计划中的设施 将对此进行支持
So congratulations to everyone involved,
那么 恭喜每一个参与发射的人员
the designers, the engineers, the pilots and of course the awesome Cosmic Girl.
设计师 工程师 飞行员 当然还有最棒的宇宙女孩
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]